the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to perform for the final
time this season welcome back friends
I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a professor of
Kinesiology in the center for sport
performance at Cal Fullerton so far in
the first season of perform we've talked
about everything from muscle to the
immune system to liver and lungs
metabolism genetics sleep blood work and
so I thought we have to end this thing
on what I hate giving credit to because
I'm a muscle guy but probably deserves
it and that's the brain there are
obviously many factors that go into
getting your brain to perform at its
best but today I want to focus
specifically on what you can do from a
nutrition perspective to reduce your
risk of as well as recover faster from
brain injuries concussions and tbis I
think it's worth reminding you though
that if it's good for preventing and
returning faster from a brain injury
it's probably safe to assume it's also
good for brain performance as well as
long-term Health now I'm particularly
passionate about this subject having
dealt with it a lot personally I've had
a concussion or two myself and I've
spent much of my career working with
athletes prone or at high risk of
developing similar injuries this is
includes football players wrestlers
Fighters boxers and so forth that said
those are not the only people at risk of
a brain injury in fact those things are
quite common and not only in athletes so
I'm really excited about this topic
because brain injuries are really common
they can be completely debilitating and
there's actually a lot of evidence that
nutrition and supplementation can have a
big effect in again both reducing your
risk of getting one as well as coming
back faster once they've happened and so
I really want to make sure everyone
knows what their options are from a
supplementation as well as Whole Food
perspective on getting back and
returning as fast as possible and
minimizing the symptoms of brain
injuries now as I was saying traumatic
brain injuries or what we'll refer to as
tbis are really common in fact a lot of
people in the field refer to them as the
invisible disease because they don't
come with a physical appearance there's
no cut there's no bruise or joint
sticking the wrong way bone poking out
of the skin and so these things can
happen and you don't necessarily know
that an injury occurred other problems
include the fact that the symptoms that
are associated with TBI or concussion
are really similar to those generally
associated with aging so you talk about
memory recall issues mood sleep and
other things that people don't
necessarily know are because of an
injury and they may think it's just due
to normal aging in fact we'll get into
this a lot as the episode progresses but
a lot of the research on brain health
with aging Alzheimers dementia and other
related topics come from the same data
sets that we work on for tbis and
concussions and the inverse so there's a
huge overlap or vend diagram between the
types of research the study design the
actual papers themselves the
interventions the models whether we're
talking about data from humans or
animals and rats and ferrets and things
like that there's a large overlap
between these two bases they're
different of course and we'll try to
highlight those but these are some of
the reasons why I want to get into
today's episode even if you're not an
athlete cuz many of you still at risk of
getting a TBI in fact the vast majority
of concussions and tbis do not come from
Sports they come from accidental slips
and falls and other problems like that
in addition they're still going to tell
us a lot of indirect information about
overall healthy brain aging so the goal
here will be to reduce our risk of
course but if it does occur to minimize
the symptoms and return back to a
healthy brain as fast as possible now
before we go too much further I'd like
to take a quick break and thank our
sponsors because they make this show
possible not only are they on this list
because they offer great products and
services but because I actually
personally love them and use them myself
today's episode is brought to you by
element element is an electrolyte drink
mix that has an ideal ratio of sodium
potassium and magnesium but has no sugar
electrolytes are critical to proper
hydration which I've been harping on for
years but you can't do that by only
drinking water in fact many of you will
probably remember that I featured
element in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration all the way back in
2020 which is obviously long before this
podcast even existed so I've been a fan
of element for a long time in fact as
stute listeners will also realize these
hydration videos were the Genesis of the
Galpin hydration equation named not by
me but by the legendary neuroscientist
Dr Andrew huberman I featured element in
these videos because they're blend of
1,000 Mig of sodium 200 Mig potassium
and 6 Mig magnesium really is different
than any other electrolyte on the market
and has great scientific support I
personally use the Citrus and watermelon
flavors a ton to preh hydrate before
heading out on a full day of training or
long hike or a hunt since I know I'll be
losing a bunch of fluids and won't have
many opportunities to take things with
me element has also just released a new
line of canned sparkling element which I
am all about if you'd like to try
element you can go to drink LM nt.com
perform to claim a free element sample
pack with the purchase of any element
drink mix again that's drink LM nt.com
perform to claim a free sample pack
today's episode is also brought to you
by Continuum Continuum is a membership
only wellness club designed to help high
performers reach their Fitness and
performance goals Continuum just opened
its Flagship Club in Manhattan quickly
making it one of the most sought-after
memberships in the city its location in
Greenwich Village is incredible in fact
it's stunning it's a 20 5,000 ft space
with state-of-the-art equipment a
beautiful design and everything you
could possibly want in this unique mix
of a gym Wellness Center and Social Club
Continuum members start with a thorough
Olympic grade assessment that results in
a biometrically driven AI assisted
wellness program that updates in real
time and incorporates everything from
personal training and physical therapy
to Hyperbaric and IV therapies by
bringing together true Fitness Experts
best-in-class technology and proven
Wellness services and amenities
Continuum delivers the most
comprehensive solution to Performance
I've been involved with Continuum
working as their head of performance
science since their founding and I've
been incredibly impressed by what the
team there has built if you're
interested in joining Continuum their
team has agreed to give a select number
of you the listeners here a fully waved
onboarding which includes VO2 max
testing dexas scans blood panels sleep
analysis and more all at their Fabulous
New York City Flagship location to learn
more visit continuum. club/ perform
again that's Continuum with two use.
Club perform now before we get started
on the details I want to highlight a
couple of things first remember I have a
PhD I am a Scientist I've published in
this area in fact I have recently
submitted a literature review as a
co-author we'll talk about that later
but I'm not a medical doctor if you
think you have any risk of or
potentially have had or suffering
consequences from
any type of brain related injury please
see a medical professional in this area
I want to focus this episode on
nutrition and supplementation related to
brain injury but I also don't want
anyone to think that I'm suggesting this
is all you should do for your brain
injury I also don't want anyone to think
that I'm suggesting this is enough to
stop your chances of ever having a brain
injury so that being said the landscape
of the research and many the scientists
and they area are on the same page in
the fact that there is emerging evidence
that several micronutrients and what
we'll call biological compounds really
do have the ability to reduce the risk I
hesitate to say prevent but can help
prevent and treat brain injuries
concussions tbis and related events now
over the course of today's show I'm
going to walk you through a bunch of
different micronutrient and
nutriceutical options you have we'll
cover the evidence how much to take the
protocol and so on and so forth but
before we do that you have to actually
understand a little bit of the
terminology because depending on what
type of brain injury you have you may
want to take a different route with your
nutrition so getting going with that
point what is a brain injury you've
heard me now say concussion TBI brain
health and a bunch of different terms
like that what is actually the
difference in fact do you even know the
difference between a TBI and a
concussion it's been my experience that
most people don't
and so we'll maybe just start right
there right so a brain injury can mean a
lot of different things honest answer
here there's not that much research in
humans and randomized control trials on
what to do to prevent or reduce an
injury in fact if you think about
research design that's really hard to do
the only way to execute these kinds of
studies in humans is to set up an
enrollment center say at a hospital
probably around an area that has a lot
of kids playing in sports wait for
people to show up with an injury ask
them if you can enroll them in a study
and go on from that we can't go out and
give humans head injuries and
concussions and so it's really
challenging it's hard to get an adequate
sample size and you're also relying upon
those people coming into the study
having the same type of brain injury and
we know that that does not happen and so
brain injuries themselves there's a lot
to learn and there's lots of different
types it would be foolish to think that
we know how to prevent all of them or
recover from all of them some types of
injuries we know more about other types
we know way less and so there's not one
type which means there's not one
solution and this is going to explain
why almost always you will see mixed
results easy example here we're going to
talk about one of the major problems
that are associated with brain injuries
is sleep so supplements that help with
sleep therefore are going to be helpful
for folks who are experiencing sleep
sleep related problems with the brain
injury however if you have a brain
injury and we're not suffering symptoms
of sleep loss then a sleep aid may or
may not actually work if both those
individuals let's say we had two people
one having issues with sleep one not
both enrolled in the same study you're
going to see the magnitude of effect of
the supplement or the nutritional Factor
gets a little bit washed out so those
are common themes you will see I won't
bring this up again because honestly I
could do that with just about every
single stuff
but it's something for you to really
consider in the back of your mind all
right now the goal then is to present to
you information that I think has a
strength of evidence I'll explain to you
what my C criteria for a strong evidence
is a little bit later and things that I
think kind of justify what we'll call
low risk and high potential reward we'll
typically break those down into things
you can do before the injury during or
immediately after the injury as well as
long-term post recovery so you can think
about that as pre per or post or simply
preventative and then treatments post
injury so in terms of terminology I'm
going to try to be consistent with three
basic phrases so a brain injury is often
broken up into three categories based on
the severity there's mild which is the
lowest moderate and severe now
fortunately mild is by far the most
common in fact some papers will indicate
that over 90 plus percent of brain
injuries are qualified as mild what that
means typically is there is a 30 minute
or less change in state of
consciousness right so if you were
unconscious for a couple of minutes you
probably had a mild traumatic brain
injury right this is often associated
with things like confusion or
post-traumatic impact Amnesia right so
you you know forgot what happened
immediately afterwards or you had a
little bit of a time travel as I like to
call it and this can occur a couple of
hours or even up to one day is the
general line that we cross there the
overwhelming majority of recreational
and Sport related concussions fall into
this category therefore almost always
though not always but almost always when
you hear the word concussion you can
generally translate that into a mild TBI
now not all TBI are
concussions but all concussions are tbis
okay so one more time in case I cost you
there concussion is effectively a mild
traumatic brain injury based on those
categories if you had worse effects so
you were unconscious for longer or your
Amnesia were lasted longer then you may
be actually be considered to being a
moderate category so moderate
technically is defined as a loss of
consciousness or amnesia for somewhere
between 30 minutes to up to 24
hours symptoms associated with this are
more severe it is headaches confusion
dizziness nausea vomiting slurge speech
drowsiness difficulty concentrating so
on and so forth and so another kind of
back of the envelope way to
differentiate between mild and moderate
is mild again not always but rough
guidelines here mild is fairly acute so
in and immediately after the injury you
had symptoms but then you're usually
back to normal moderate often comes with
Downstream problems not the injury
themselves so this is when you have beh
behavioral changes because of the TBI
you've got again difficulty with memory
that lasts a long time that's again back
of the envelope kind of Distinction if
it is worse than that we call it severe
that is technically a loss of
consciousness or amnesia for somewhere
between 2 24 hours to up to or more than
seven days and moderate and
severe also have similar dementia like
symptoms now I mentioned this earlier
but think about this severe tbis
oftentimes come with memory and
attention problems decision-making
problems learning impairments mood Big
Sleep disturbances and so you can
imagine somebody who's in their 50s 60s
or 70s Who start experiencing things
like that they may personally just think
oh this is I'm getting old family
members may think oh Grandma's got you
know starting to show dementia signs
could be possible could also be possible
that Grandma's simply suffering from a a
severe TBI
and so this is what I was referring to
earlier when I said there is actually a
big crossover here it's a bit of a gray
area they can actually be the same thing
they can clearly be different as well
but there is a large crossover between
them so hopefully that helps you
understand a little bit about what the
difference between a concussion and a
TBI is what a mild moderate and severe
traumatic pain injury R and I started
sneaking in some of the physiology about
at least what's the symptoms what are
the behavioral and actual
consequences that is important to
understand because now that'll tell us
what we do in terms of a treatment or
prevention strategy in order to finally
connect that dot though we got to walk
through just a touch and I promise this
will be just a touch of the physiology
or
pathophysiology of each one of these
categories so we understand what we're
trying to do with the nutrition or the
micronutrient why they solve those
problems and then ultimately how that
translates into reduction or
of these symptoms so what's actually
happening in the brain when we
experience any of these three levels of
a brain injury there's a couple of
resources I want to give you if you want
to learn more about this right now I
based a lot of this episode heavily off
of these papers so I want to give them
their due credit they will of course be
linked and PDFs will be available in the
show notes you can find those at perform
podcast.com but for those of you who
want to write it down right now a paper
that I found particularly helpful came
out just last year in 2023 and that is
titled optimization of nutrition after
brain injury mechanistic and therapeutic
considerations in addition to that my
friend and colleague Dan Garner has a
product available for purchase on Amazon
called the brain Synergy protocol and I
will talk about that a little bit later
and then finally I honestly took the
vast majority of this episode off of a
paper that I co-authored and that's
depending on when you're listening to
this either in review or potentially
published by now
called mitigating traumatic brain injury
a narrative review of supplementation
and dietary protocols this was led by
Tommy wood the Fantastic neuroscientist
at the University of Washington and was
first authored by Federica kti another
tremendous neuroscientist in her own
right so they did the bulk of the work
here we contribute on this paper
together and I thought it was honestly
so perfect for a show that I thought I'm
just going to take this entire thing and
make a whole episode out of it but
nonetheless let's get into the paper
right now so what's actually happening
in your brain when you experience an
injury typically we've been told that
when you have some sort of injury you
have to go through this Whiplash
experience so you have a say a sudden
stop your brain inside your skull
continues to travel and then smashes up
against your skull and then therefore
has a bruise on the brain and while that
certainly can happen that's actually
probably pretty
unlikely generally what's going to
happen if that occurred is you would see
the injury site being on the outside
right so you can imagine let's just say
the front of of your brain smashes into
the front of your skull you would expect
the injury to be right on the front on
the outside part of your brain reality
of it is that's not where most
concussions and tbis occur It generally
happens more towards the middle of the
brain remember the outside of the brain
is where your gray matter is that's
mostly where your neurons are on the
inside is the white matter that's made
of mostly fat and it helps you conduct
uh messages more quickly throughout the
brain see what typically happens in
brain injuries is you get more of what I
call the accordion effect and so you
have so much fluid in your brain that if
you were to SOS it around a little bit
it there's not much room to Sash and so
it protects your brain from hitting the
skull but what can happen though is an
intense pressure inside the tissue
because it squeezes together and then
gets expanded back out picture the
accordion here me taking my two hands
putting them closer together smashing it
pulling it back apart and so you have
this kind of egg looking oval that that
is supposed to be your brain and it gets
smashed down into a vertical piece of
paper and then extended way back out and
stretched and so on and so forth so it's
not the actual connection or contact to
the skull that is always the issue
sometimes it's that stretching and
pulling and that pressure wave that caus
the damage on the interior or various
portions of the brain and so the
injuries are highly varied in the brain
it can be everything from a capillary or
blood flow Supply that is damaged or
torn the Axon themselves can be torn
this then causes a host of issues that
we'll get into step by step but it's
everything from temperature problems
energy problems um metabolism problems
inflammation and physical structural
damage so many different options that
can occur but that's basically what
happens for most but not all this is
obviously a complicated area I don't
mean to oversimplify it depending on if
you had a single event say a car crash
or a single slip and fall or numerous
subconcussive events think of blast
injuries in folks in the military um
small impacts with combat athletes or
other people in professions that kind of
bang their head a little bit don't he
necessarily get huge symptoms but they
have a lot of these stack over time all
of it results in different problems I'm
just trying to highlight a small example
of of what it can look like as a quick
overview that being said there are some
generalities and commonalities between
different forms of tbis and I'll just
cover them broadly right now the top of
our list here is what's called comprised
excitotoxicity I'll explain what that
means later but this is arguably one of
the bigger problems you will experience
there are ionic disturbances so your
positive and negative charges get all
messed up there are blood flow to the
brain that's called cerebral blood flow
edemas and swellings oxidative stress
inflammation and then as I mentioned
before even damaged or even death in the
cells that are directly in in the brain
or related to the brain that can
actually be going on acutely for weeks
or even months to decades throughout
life so I can't go over all of this it
would take me the entire show if not
many but I do want to cover a couple of
very specific examples so you can start
to grasp what this could look like the
first one is just if you've had
capillaries burst so remember you have
capillaries that surround all tissue in
your body and that's where all of your
blood exchanges happen so you have this
network in this bed of capillaries that
surround your brain when those burst you
can't get nutrients and fuel in and you
can't get waste products out and so in
the most fundamental problem here is you
don't get oxygen to the brain so we lose
cerebral blood flow we lose energy
production because we're not getting
fuel into the brain because we've
physically torn capillaries right this
if this was on your arm like it is on
mine right now you might have a purple
and black arm thank you Cam hannes but
in your brain you wouldn't see that this
goes right back to the invisible disease
problem from
earlier more detailed example would be
the following though often times we'll
break up TBI into what we call the
initial response and then the delayed or
Phase 2 response so let's say you had
some sort of Direct Hit again pick your
example it might look something like
this your initial response would be an
overactivation of the neurons that's
right the nerves that are associated
with the injury area become overly
activated now this initial response is
caused in large part by what's called
overactivation of neighboring neurons so
you remember all the nerves connected
one to one to one they're not actually
physically connected there's a small
space in between them and they
communicate by releasing what's called
neurotransmitters so what happens in
this area is you have a damage to one it
overcommunication
okay or excitotoxicity because you're
excited so much that it comes to the
level of toxicity and excited meaning
the neurons being too active now this
happens in large part because of a
molecule called glutamate you'll see
this all over the TP TBI literature
supplementation marketing very common to
be talked about because it is very real
and very important it's the main
neurotransmitter that's responsible for
this excitatory activity okay now this
gets released in response to that we
have a whole down Cascade of problems
and this starts off as an initial
response and then I'll show you how this
turns into that delayed phase response
later so we have this overe excitation
now if you go back to our episode on
muscle you'll learn more about how
nerves and cells contract why sodium and
calcium and potassium and chloride are
responsible for Action potentials and so
on and so forth for now sodium and
calcium very specifically become overly
activated in fact you literally often
times have damage to the plasma membrane
so the little thing that surrounds your
cells gets damaged gets broken and so
because of that the things that are
supposed to be in the cell and things
that are not supposed to come in the
cell start leaking everywhere so sodium
and calcium start coming in and out of
the cell in inappropriate manners now
this causes things that are eventually
going to be cell death and
degradation because of production of
what's called Ross Ross is r a reactive
oxygen species so remember oxygen is
very reactive it is good and bad you
have to have oxygen for fuel allow you
to create fuel rather it's a byproduct
needed to make aerobic metabolism at the
same time excessive amounts of it are
going to be damaging this is how we
break down tissue this is how we create
and clean out dead and debed cells and
so if we're generating way too much of
this reactive oxygen species this is
almost synonymous
every time with oxidative stress these
are these are kind of similar terms not
the exact same thing but pretty close
this also activates several enzymes that
damage the cell structure um these are
everything from what we'll call
proteases so anas is an enzyme that
breaks down a protein to lipases these
are enzymes that break down fats U
Nitric oxides synthesis and and
endonucleases and and other things like
that a whole Cask of enzymes that start
breaking the thing down you don't know
exactly what's happening here but the
cell thing thinks that there's problems
because there are and so it just starts
activating cell death so we're having
issues with that okay in addition to
that that calcium specificity becomes a
problem because it alone harms
mitochondrial health and efficiency and
so the cells that do stay alive start
getting really damaged mitochondria uh
this is again because of a membrane
damage issue that allows too much
permeability of things in and out and
that of course eliminates or drastically
reduces mitochondria's ability to work
which means your ability to make ATP
remember ATP is the cellular currency
it's the only way any living cell can
create energy and so mitochondri is not
the only way we can make ATP hold on to
that we're going to come back to that
but it is the primary way and it is the
exclusive way in which we generate
aerobic metabolism so the way that we
create fuel with oxygen has to go for
mitochondria so damaged or ineffec of
mitochondria is going to directly lead
to red reduced ATP production reduced
ATP production simply means we have way
more cellular energy in our
brain this idea of brain fog or fatigue
or can't remember things recall exective
decision if you don't have energy your
brain can't think that's quite literally
what's happening and this is why some of
the supplements and micronutrients we're
going to talk about later have such
positive effect is they help you restore
what's called that energy balance the
damage occurred you weren't able to get
transportation of oxygen and things in
this allowed permeability of calcium
this allowed too much excitation which
means we're burning too much energy at
the same time we don't create enough
energy and so we end up being in this
really catabolic or negative energy
State and now we can't think well we're
dealing with signs and symptoms and
overall more importantly our brain is
actually physically unhealthy and so
because your brain is measuring energy
production at all times it knows this
imbalance is occurring it's going to try
to alleviate it and the best way to do
that is to ramp up energy production but
since it can't do it aerobically it has
to turn to anerobic methods and
specifically what we're talking about
here is Anor robic
glycolysis one more time go back to our
previous episode I believe it was
episode two on muscle and we talk about
the physiology and bioenergetics of how
we use carbohydrates for fuel it's the
same we're in the brain here we're not
in muscle but anerobic glycolysis is
still anerobic glycolysis it's still the
breakdown of carbohydrates for the
production of ATP so in this particular
case since the ability to store glucose
in the brain is quite limited and the
amount that we can get into the brain
through the bloodb brain barrier is also
somewhat limited if we're only or mostly
relying upon anerobic glycolysis you can
quickly see we're not going to be able
to handle all the supply because not
only does the brain take an enormous
amount of energy it's in fact depending
on the situation our most energy costly
organ in the body and now it's injured
and it has more energy demands to
recover and it has less energy
production we're going to be really
running into problems with our energy
deficit so to summarize all that
effectively What's Happening Here is
you've got this disrupted cell
homeostasis this leads to all kinds of
problems like cell death or apoptosis uh
DNA fragmentation necrosis cytoskeletal
degradation and a whole host of other
things that are short and longterm and
that's just the phase one part that's
the initial response from there and once
we've dealt with that we now have to
handle step two or the delayed or second
phase which is generally associated with
neuroinflammation and prolonged
oxidative stress so what we're talking
about here is this pervasive
inflammatory Cascade that is in
combination with our metabolic changes
specifically to the blood brain barrier
now remember that's the thing that keeps
things out of your brain and in your
body and and kind of keeps the
separation there if we've got a brain
injury we potentially have damage to
that membrane as well and so we've got
excessive inflammation happening not
even talking about the acute response
now it's staying there and persisting
for days weeks months or potentially
even longer this causes uh migration of
what's called peripheral immune cells
into the brain and releases a whole
storm of cyto kindes these are
communication tools that come out of
your body from one organ to the next
they're not necessarily good or bad but
in this case it's so large and it's so
extreme that it continues to exacerbate
this inflammatory
problem uh this also causes activation
of things that are called residual
neural cells um there's a whole host of
these things like astrocytes complement
proteins and so on um these things
release reactive oxidative species they
release AC glutamate again and they
release those cyto kindes and so you can
see how this circle just sort of
perpetuates itself it's not always a bad
response but in this particular case
since there's been so much structural
damage one more time the cycle just
continues this is going to really harm
the brain's healing it's going to
facilitate formation of what are called
membrane attack
complexes you could just hear from that
term that's probably not a good thing
again we're trying to clean out the
damage but it's going to come with a lot
of problems um this is going to create
like very specifically pores in the
membranes of the the target cells which
means those are going to often die now
in the case of like a skeletal muscle
from exercise this is okay it's pretty
to repair but when it's happening in
your brain it's a problem right so
overall we've got that oxidative stress
uh response and that's going to start
damaging fat protein and DNA
remember big portion of your brain is
made of fat so while we're typically not
concerned about oxidative stress harming
all the fat in our rest of our body that
represents a serious damage to our brain
and one that potentially is not
reversible now I know I got pretty
technical there so so if I lost any of
you don't worry about it just think
about it this way at the highest level
uh TBI is going to involve some
likelihood of a physical injury or
damage this could be your capillaries or
any of your vessels your bloodb brain
barrier your membranes of your cells
your astrocytes your neurons are
actually physically torn if you were a
house this would mean your windows are
smashed your door's broken they got a
hole in a wall it's not a functionality
issue as it is an actual structure is
broken and has to be repaired now in
addition to that we're going to be
dealing with a secondary problem which
is now because we don't have the
physical structure to get in nutrients
and get waste out we can't make energy
so problem number two is a massive
energy deficit your brain's going to try
to get around it it's going to start
ramping up our less effective methods of
producing energy but it's never going to
catch up and so physical damage number
one one energy deficit number two number
three in response to number one and two
is this prolonged inflammatory response
and so we're sending in molecules that
let the inflammation continue and they
exacerbated and they start breaking down
and killing and getting rid of actual
tissue so the ones that maybe were not
injured initially will be injured or
removed entirely in the weeks to months
because of this inflammatory response
so effectively those are our three big
problems which means now we can talk
about what nutrition options we have to
solve or mitigate or at least attenuate
slightly reduce some of those issues I'd
like to take a quick break and thank our
sponsors today's episode is brought to
you by momentus momentus makes
supplements of the absolute highest
quality for example we've long known
about the numerous health and
performance benefits of fish oil I've
personally been taking it for probably
years or more now you can get fish oil
anywhere but personally I only use
momentus because it's never once given
me a fishy aftertaste and more
importantly every single batch is NSF
tested to ensure the lead and mercury
levels are undetectable for Purity and
safety their fish oil is pure potent and
sustainably sourced another major
benefit is that you won't find any
fillers in their fish oil see the dirty
secret in the industry here is that most
companies will add non EPA and dhas to
their fish oil to keep their quote fish
oil count high but to keep the active
ingredients and therefore costs low it
makes you actually feel like when you're
purchasing it you're getting more fish
oil at a cheaper price but you actually
have to double or triple your dose to
get the same amount of active ingredient
which means you end up spending more
money in the long run or you don't and
you get worse results if you want to
give their fish oil a shot or any other
momentous product go to liv.com perform
to get 20% off your order again that's
liv.com perform to get 20% off today's
episode is also brought to you by Maui
Nei venison Maui Nei venison is my
absolute favorite thing to eat period
it's beyond delicious and the highest
protein per calorie meat you will find
Maui Nei venison is 100% wild harvested
meat not fenced farmed or fed in any way
and is far beyond the quality of any
beef grass-fed or whatever you've ever
tried in your life and I know cuz I grew
up in the country and I've tried it all
it's easy to cook and tastes incredible
my wife and small kids absolutely inhale
it and the jerky sticks are a daily
staple for me with 10 grams of protein
and just 55 calories I literally ate two
just now and I send it to school with my
kids all the time while Maui Nei venison
offers the highest quality meat
available there is a catch supplies are
limited by Nature responsible population
management means they won't go beyond
the har capacity memberships are the
best way to ensure that you can get the
meat you want whenever you want it so be
sure to secure your spot now visit Maui
nen.com perform for 20% off again that's
Maui venison
docomo hydrate you're probably sick of
hearing me talk about it because I've
been doing it for so many years but it's
for good reason there's so much data on
it it is by far the most widely studied
sport supplement and it's not even close
it's been studied in every
population healthy diseased young old
men women kids so on and so forth and
there's really very limited side effects
if any that have been reported now
creatine itself is a naturally occurring
derivative of three very specific amino
acids methine Glycine and Arginine these
are really really common uh creatine
itself I typically have talked about how
it's stored in muscle and used as a
great fuel source but many people don't
realize it's actually also stored in
your liver testes and brain the last one
of course is where we're going to pay
our attention to today now it's stored
in the brain so that it can be used as a
very quick fuel source your gear should
be turning at this point remember one of
the primary issues we have with the TBI
is that energy demand problem and so it
made a ton of sense to scientists very
early on to say okay we know that we
have energy issues we know that the fast
way any of our tissues can make energy
is through creting monohydrate and we
know it's in stored in the brain already
it makes sense to try that to both
prevent or reduce the risk of and then
treat brain injuries so it's no surprise
when we look at the research here on
both TBI as well as aging and normal
brain health research to find that
monohydrate often improves
cognitive function in both brain injury
and normal healthy aging folks now it's
not the world's most powerful neut
tropic I but it is effective and been
shown again in many models and many
studies across many Laboratories so
because it's so effective at giving
energy especially in low oxygen
situations you'll see evidence across
injury in TBI papers but also just
normal cognitive function and healthy
individuals uh to see benefit right so
creatin is effective in all of those
populations and the physiology
biochemistry make total sense now
specifically regarding tbis and ions one
of the things you want to pay attention
to a lot is What's called the second
impact
syndrome many people have not heard of
this but this is the basic idea of
repeated head blows cause more
damage as time goes on and so one of the
things that's been shown with creatine
is is really effective for that second
impact syndrome more specifically it's
been shown that the repeated head blows
cause more damage if the creatine is
depleted prior to the additional impacts
okay so imagine you had an one single
impact the more creatine depletion you
have the worse damage you get if you
have a secondary
impact this is any athlete that's going
to be in sparring our competitions where
we're getting a lot of impacts this is
military or special forces or anything
like that that is again is getting low
impact repeated exposures or blasts okay
the more creatine depletion that happens
the worse the damage in your brain that
occur occurs after the second or
repeated impact so right there we can
see that if you've had an injury making
sure your creatine stores are
replenished as quickly as possible is
really important if we're going to
continue in that
exposure now that's important because
many people don't recognize or realize
the first injury happened to begin with
okay most of them are underreported most
don't realize it hard to diagnose and so
prophylactically it just maybe makes
some sense to make sure that you're
taking care of business not necessarily
just when you have an injury but if you
even think you're at risk or in
high-risk situations or prior to
high-risk exposures or or
competitions right good example of this
there's a pretty famous study I think it
was in high school football players high
school or college but nonetheless
football players American football that
is um that did indicate the creatine
stores in their brain I think
specifically in the motor and prefrontal
cortex reduced over the course of the
season now this is not a perfect study
design
but you can see what this is alluding to
if you're in a situation again with
repeated him head impacts over the
course of his season the number of
impacts so in fact maybe I'll back up
quickly in this particular study what
they did is they filmed the games and so
what they they measured is for each
individual player how many head contacts
they had but there was an association
between those players that had more head
impacts not even necessarily injuries
and the level of creatine reduction in
the brain over the course of the season
so again we're making some assumptions
here but I think it's fair to at least
say it's
plausible the more impacts on your brain
the more creatine is reduced potentially
the higher risk you are for second
impact syndrome injuries now before we
go any further with the creatine
research I need to do a quick pause and
explain to you what I mean when I say
strong evidence or weak evidence there's
no perfect way to do that but an easy
way to roughly understand is called the
strength of evidence scale okay so I
will abbreviate that in the rest of
today's episode by just calling it the S
OE the strength of evidence okay this
takes into account research design the
quality of the relevant studies the
applicability to Patient Care and a
number of other factors it's up to you
ultimately to decide what is an
actionable level of evidence or not some
people that are may be suffering from a
brain injury consider a study in animals
to be enough and others want to see a
randomized control trial in humans
that's not for me to decide that's up to
you but I do want to share with you
where the level of evidence is and you
can make your choice from there so the S
OE is on a scale of one to five a score
of one is the best that is the highest
score possible this means we see
consistent results across multiple
studies we've seen it in both randomized
control trials as well as systematic
reviews and so on and so forth a score
of say four four or five would be the
opposite that would be our lowest score
maybe there's evidence there but it's
from case studies or case control
studies maybe it's mechanism only or
some other model that's close maybe
research from aging or demena not the
same as brain injury but it shares some
mechanisms you get the idea here so for
example the soe for monohydrate
is a two my opinion personally that's
pretty good summarizing the colle
evidence here there's been a lot of
research on everything from kids to
rugby players to mountain bikers and
collectively you're going to see it
supports cognitive Health it's been
shown actually in psychiatric disorders
there's I believe two randomized control
trials that I'm aware of that have found
five grams of creatine per day um added
in addition to anti-depressant
treatments improved depressive symptoms
right so take that for what you will and
regarding TBI and brain injuries
there's an argument we can make here for
preventative use specifically for
neuronal damage and injury there's been
shown to reduce cortical damage
following a TBI by anywhere between 35
to
50% that'd be 5 Z pretty substantial
amount there should catch your
attention they don't know exactly how it
works but it's thought to prevent some
of that mitochondrial dysfunction I was
talking about a few minutes ago uh helps
maintain the membrane
Health certainly has a role in fending
off that Downstream reactive oxygen
species ATP calcium so a lot of those
things we just got done covering that's
why we covered them creatine probably
has a role again we need more
information here but likely has a role
in in either eliminating or at least
drastically reducing some of those
issues and finally then what you care
more about is the downstream TBI effects
have also been documented what I mean
here is sleep cognition and actual mood
seem to be enhanced with the Crea team
furthermore there's actually some
studies that specifically been done on
kids there's one I'm thinking of in
detail here that was everything from 1
to 18y olds that had severe tbis in this
particular paper they gave them 0.4 gram
per kilogram of body weight if you do
the math there that ends up being a a
pretty standard dose but appropriately
it was done based on body size you have
2year olds and 18y olds we can't give
them all just five gram so dose was
given to them within 4 hours post injury
and done so for 6 months in that
particular study they found improvements
in everything from Amnesia to the length
of stay in the ICU improvements in
communication Locomotion and social
skills and more importantly what I one
of the things I loved most about this
was this the researchers were clear in
the fact that the treatment provided
cost significantly less than the
standard treatment protocol
and this is something I thought was
really important because I know
supplements are not cheap and many of
you can't afford any cost whatsoever but
if you can while creatine I know I know
I hear this all the time has gotten more
expensive in re recent years it's still
likely far cheaper than a standard
Hospital protocol so if you can possibly
afford it seems to be a pretty good
option another thing I want to point out
here because it comes up all the time as
well in this study again remember Kids 6
months of Crea
there were no signs of any kidney liver
or heart side effects so overall we
would deem creatine as a pretty strong
chance of success in both the physiology
as well as actual symptoms with a very
low likelihood of injury or adverse
effects for me personally I wouldn't
hesitate to give this to one of my kids
if they have it it's entirely up to you
to make your choice I'm not advocating
you do anything you don't want to do are
uncomfortable with just letting you know
for me when I look at the research as a
parent myself of two young kids I I
would not hesitate at all to use this in
my children so how do you actually use
creatine well you have a couple of
options one you can try to get this from
Whole Foods and I'll present to you
exactly what that would mean in amounts
or you can use the supplementation route
I guess a third option would be to use a
combination of both so most of the data
on monohydrate for brain injuries
they're typically using dosages of about
20 grams per day now that's four times
the typical dose you'll see for
performance benefits so this is one of
our major things we have to pay
attention to this is not a dosage that's
just your standard five grams five grams
five grams it is much higher for the the
brain health benefits now often times
that's a little bit challenging and so
you'll see typical protocols instead of
taking 20 grams at once are things like
five GRS administered four times per day
right so the the benefits are typically
thought of as both acute and chronic I
know I have said many many many years
now that a is not an acute thing
it's not caffeine you don't take
right now and feel this big stimulation
effects it takes weeks or months to
build up
however one paper that came out recently
kind of shook everyone's World a 2024
paper get just one paper here so temper
a little bit I'm tempering my own
expectations but a recent paper
suggested that a very high dose I think
it was
35 gram per kilogram of body weight was
enough to attenuate the drop in
cognitive performance after sleep
deprivation so you take people through
sleep deprivation the next day you give
them this giant bullets of creatine and
those that took the creatine had less of
a cognitive drop from sleep deprivation
I actually think the benefit started at
about 3 and 1/2 hours and lasted up to 9
hours so potentially say something bad
happened happed and you didn't get a
great night of sleep and you could take
this maybe 20 G dose in the morning and
by noon or so or for the rest of the day
you might have some improvements in
cognitive function that's the first
paper I've ever seen that I'm aware of
to show an acute effect of creatine but
since that was so dramatic I wanted to
make sure I drew it to your attention so
to me you have an option there for brain
health and now if we consider this in
context of the episode of today even
getting this creatine in immediately
potentially has a brain impact and
that's why I wanted to bring that study
up as it relates to the current topic
other Studies have found that that 20
grams per day for 7 Days enhances
cognitive function um this is
specifically the mountain biker study
I'm referring to and so generally me
personally this is not the studies this
is me personally based on the work that
I've read I think 5 to 10 gram per day
is probably plenty for most people as a
prophylactic so kind of an ongoing
option to be at that number that said
and again candidly this is what I do for
my athletes seven days or so prior to a
high-risk situation a competition
something like that a race or an event
we're going to up that dose to 20 to 30
grams for that seven days all right
again one more time when I do that it it
is hard to choke down 20 grams at once
it's a handful of Scoops and so we will
often try to get 5 to 10 gram in the
morning 5 to 10 gram at night and split
up the dosages throughout the day simply
from my practical perspective now one of
my favorite sayings is there are no free
passes in physiology creatine is not
perfect it's not a Panacea and there are
some potential risks the biggest one is
GI distress some people have gas or
bloating or stomach cramps at even five
grams a day so taking them to 20 or 30
may cause some serious issues it's not
that frequently reported I've never
experienced it
I can't think of a situation where I've
ever had an athlete or client reported
but it is a real thing it is pretty
uncommon but is reported and so you will
want to pay attention to that outside of
that there isn't really any documented
problems associated even with high
dosages 20 plus grams a day for years
there have been studies in kids elderly
various what we'll call risky or
unhealthy populations for many many
years you can look across all basically
all those studies and you just won't
find really any other Adverse Events
outside of the possible mild or moderate
GI distress now if the supplement does
give you GI distress or you can't afford
it don't have access to it or for any
other reason just don't like supplements
you can theoretically get here with food
but it is admittedly very challenging
especially for those vegans and
vegetarians cuz the primary source of
creat from food comes from muscle or
meat the most common places of
and meat are going to be things like
beef chicken salmon tuna Cod and they
mostly have somewhere between 400 to 600
milligrams of creatine per 100 G of meat
now I know in America you're thinking
what the hell is 100 gram the rest of
the world knows exactly what that means
but 100 grams is about 3 and 1 12 ounces
okay a typical serving size at a
restaurant
is you know 7 o or so and so you can
kind of double it in other words beef
specifically has 600 milligrams of
creatine per 100 gram but a typical
serving is 200 gram so you'd be getting
1200 millgram 1200 milligram is also 1.2
gram okay now the average American at
least eats about 350 grams or 12 ounces
of meat per day so if you did some basic
math there which would mean you're at
about 2,000 milligrams or 2 gram of
creatine per day so while it is possible
theoretically to get all your creatine
from food it's honestly quite
challenging so supplementation just
might be the better option in this case
I'd like to take a quick break and thank
our sponsors today's episode is brought
to you by ag1 ag1 is a foundational
nutrition greens supplement that means
ag1 provides a variety of vitamins
minerals probiotics prebiotics and
adaptogens in an easy to drink greens
powder initially I was very skeptical of
ag1 as I am with all supplement
companies frankly but after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition
scientists and the team at ag1 I've been
impressed by their commitment to
sourcing the highest quality ingredients
and rigorous testing to ensure that
every single batch is free of banned
substances allergens heavy metals
microbes pesticides herbicides residual
solvents and microt toxins it's Sten
earned the prestigious NSF certified for
sport third-party testing approval now
ag1 is not a replacement for eating
Whole Foods but it is a great way to
fill in the gaps and it's been a big
help pushing some of my clients just in
the right direction for eating more
highquality Foods because it helps them
with Cravings digestion and many other
benefits now not everyone needs to
consume greens powders but if you're
going to do so you better make sure it
actually includes the ingredients that
it claims to and that those ingredients
are of the best sourcing if you'd like
to try ag1 you can go to drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus K2 again that's drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus K2 today's episode is also brought
To Us by David David makes protein bars
unlike anything I've ever encountered
they have an amazing 28 g of protein
only 150 calories and 0 g of sugar
that's right 28 g of protein and 75% of
its calories come from protein this is
50% higher than the next closest protein
bar honestly it's the best tasting
protein bar I've ever had in my life by
a mile now I don't usually talk about
products before their launch but These
Bars by David represent a meaningful
breakthrough in both macronutrients and
taste and when you guys try it you will
know what I mean after lots of research
and development these David protein bars
are releasing to the public in September
of
2024 the macronutrients one more time
are 28 Gams of protein 150 calories and
0 gram of sugar and they do this with
excellent ingredients if you're
interested in trying these bars for
yourself you can go to
david.com perform to purchase if
possible or be notified when they're
available again that's
david.com perform to purchase if
possible or be notified when they are
available our next topic is fish oil
more specifically what I mean here is
DHA and EPA DHA is accumulated in the
brain in fact it's about 10% of your
brain or so so makes a lot of sense that
this one's going to be pretty important
it's critical for everything from
neurological function to injury risk
metabolic rate uh prevention of neurod
degeneration aging and brain health and
Alzheimer's Dimension so on and so forth
incredibly important to actual structure
EPA is a little bit different it's
mainly involved in vascular function
inflammation oxygen delivery uh nutrient
delivery to the brain and so on and so
forth right so these are typically tied
together so I'm not going to really
differentiate them as most Omega-3s come
with both EPA and D now while I said
earlier that creatine is by far the most
studied sport supplement because it is
Omega-3s are by far the most studied
regarding traumatic brain injury there
are dozens and dozens of studies
systematic reviews randomized control
trials on Omega-3s and brain related
injuries and various head traumas
however you might be surprised to know
I'm not aware of any direct evidence of
Omega-3s and tbis so this is a great
example of me saying hey look there's
still a lot of good tangential or
indirect evidence here so much I feel
like it's overwhelming but not
necessarily that much directly on tbis
for the reasons we described earlier
they're just hard study to carry out in
general what you're going to see is
frankly they work they work for both pre
and post impacts the soe is technically
three here and you generally see main
effects and benefits from cerebral
profusion so this is getting that blood
and oxygen and and flow of nutrients in
and out of the brain remember the
primary cause of injury there is that
structural that tissue and that axon
shearing that that kind of ripping apart
and so what that does does is cause that
Cascade of secondary insults that
mismatch the blood flow and the
metabolic demand we talked about that
earlier omega-3 is land right on that
problem uh for Solutions and the reason
is it helps dramatically with what's
called arterial pliability and
compliance and so when we're having
issues getting blood in the arteries can
either be broke or damaged or stiff and
Omega-3s really help it become more
pliable and open and close more itively
is one way to think about it it's also
why you see so much evidence in research
on Omega thees for heart health and
blood pressure and so on and so forth
has the same effect essentially in the
brain other thing it does that's a huge
benefit outside of that cerebral
profusion is it modulates inflammation
post injury by regulating that Ross
reactive auction species it interacts
with all kinds of cyto kindes like
interlukin one and tnf Alpha if you're
familiar with those if not don't worry
about it um even actually there's one in
particular called nfkb that brain folks
will know exactly what I'm talking about
here um this actually functionally it
affects a gene expression of a bunch of
inflammatory things so it kind of cuts
off inflammation at the genetic level so
lots of ways that it has an impact to
give you a couple specific examples one
of the most common issues associated
with
TBI longterm is called atrophy of the
hippocampus now that's associated in one
of the areas that's mainly responsible
for learning and memory and we know that
those are problems right we know that
higher omega-3 intake is associated with
a bigger hippocampal volume right so we
have cross-sectional studies here
longitudinal ones that suggesting in
people that consume more tend to have a
larger hippo campus and we also see a
significant increase in these areas at
the dosage of about 2.2 grams per day
okay 2.2 grams of fici oil per day
associated with a bigger hippocampus
therefore potential to improve or
enhance our learning in memory similar
things have been done with memory
specifically in fact one study looked at
I think it was a combination of 900 Mig
of EPA plus 260 Mig of DHA and that
resulted in greater accuracy and speed
of recall tasks so mental recall memory
EPA in general is often really
associated with cognitive function and
the DHA is associated with acdal
injuries um works on a thing called
neurofilament light or NFL and that's
actually been specifically shown in
college football players I believe again
at that 2 G per day dosage of
DHA so in general to get to the end here
the dosage for brain related injuries is
somewhere between 2 to four grams per
day though there's really little risk
the only adverse issue you're going to
typically have here is potentially some
loose
stool again there's not that much
evidence of it but if you have a you
consume a bunch of oil that can kind of
run through you a little bit probably
not going to see much happen there very
often the time timing of it doesn't
matter that much you can you would
certainly want to be taking it before
the injury as well as after the injury
and the timing of the day is honestly
totally irrelevant and so pretty easy
pretty fast one to go through very
effective I personally will be totally
honest I take a lot more than four grams
for other benefits but very fairly the
available evidence on not necessarily
directly TBI rcts but the other
Associated areas of brain health and
injury and damage pretty consistently
show the effect happens at about two or
so grams and studies that have looked at
higher dosages don't see any additional
benefit so I think it's very fair to say
two grams a day or so is the effective
dose and more than that may not give you
additional benefit what's that look like
from food another example where vegans
and
vegetarians really should honestly
strongly consider supplementation here
we're going to get fish oil from fish
pretty obviously right salmon Herring
sardines Macer trout are generally the
most highest concentration ones salmon
being the most obvious example that's
got about 2 gam of fish oil per 100 gram
of cooked meat again that' be 3 and a
half ounces or so which is not an
outrageous dosage at all unfortunately
the standard American diet is typically
about 100 milligrams of Omega-3s per day
and we need you to get to to two all
right so you're going to have to up your
an it's totally possible but most people
just don't do enough of it this is a
really important one to go after I know
I just covered information but I want to
also highlight the fact you can check
what I mean by that is unlike creatine
where it's going to be really hard to
measure your creatine monohydrate
especially in your brain levels you as a
preventative strategy should look at
your omega-3 index and identify whether
you have problems because there's a lot
of evidence to suggest if you go into a
brain injury with the better omega-3 the
brain injury will be less significant so
our starting place here is to actually
not go into the injury with a problem I
mentioned this but I'll be more clear
the omega-3 index is not a perfect way
to measure it but it is an effective
blood test you can get done and what
that's going to effectively tell you is
the percentage of EPA and DHA that's in
the membrane of your red blood cells and
there's been a handful of studies on
this that are quite impressive my
opinion um studies on football players
and even uh basketball players have
found that the mass majority of them
have an omega-3 index of less than 5%
optimal is like 8 to 10 maybe even 12
the overwhelming majority of these
athletes are less than five in fact I
think the studies I'm thinking of right
now uh the two kind of combined
basically none of the athletes had
higher than 7% again 8 to 12 is what
we're looking for in fact the reason
we're doing that is because there's been
known and shown documented cognitive
benefits at 10% plus even as low as A8 %
plus so in these studies no athletes are
there in fact most of the over 50% of
the athletes in these studies had an
omega3 index of less than 4% so it is
really really really common in our
athletes to see omega-3 status being
really insufficient and the same thing
has happened in the general population
so you can 100% achieve enough for brain
health through food if you'd like you
just need to make a considered effort
for it and you can see and and go back
to hear the dose just or you can use
supplements or a combination but you
absolutely want to make sure that you're
doing this
prophylactically as well as if you do
experience an injury getting right on
the supplementation as quickly as you
can next up is what's called vitamin B2
or ribal flavor we're going into ribo
Flava next because it is a requirement
for proper DHA utilization here's what I
mean there's some really nice studies
showing that if you give people DHA but
they have insufficient B2 B6 B 9 B12 and
choline they won't integrate that DHA
into their brain so it's really really
hard technically to get the DHA to
integrate into the phospholipid membrane
without these B vitamins and so part and
partial to our appropriate omega-3
status is making sure we're not vitamin
B deficient and specifically in this
case we're talking about
riboflavin so it is a co-enzyme for ATP
production it's a part of many of our
energy production Cycles it's also High
responsible for glutathione you'll hear
me bring this up again but glutathione
is our chief endogenous antioxidant it's
the big Whopper okay so going back to
our problems associated with injury
riboflavin is going to play a role in
two of those ones energy production as
well as inflammation or antioxidant
capacity so really helpful from that
regard right since we know TBI has
metabolic problems it makes sense that
these B2 and other B vitamins are going
to probably play important role the soe
on ribal flaven is a three now
personally that's enough for me to take
action you're welcome to choose your own
level I've AC on a score here but I have
utilized and will probably continue to
utilize Rial flaven for head related
injuries there's great data in Rat
studies that have shown riboflavin helps
with some of the behavioral modification
issues associated with Downstream TBI
problems humans there's not that much
research candly again that's why it has
an S soe score of three not two or one
and what we do know is there's kind of a
two studies in particular that are
classic and they both used about 400
milligrams per day one of them is a bit
older 1998 I think it was published and
it was actually in migraines and what it
showed is that it was safe and well
tolerated now interestingly this was
followed up in 2023 and they gave again
400 milligrams I think they actually did
it twice per day instead of once per day
starting 24 hours after injury I think
they had a 50 plus people in the study
and they're all about 20 years old now
in that they found a significant
reduction in the number of days of
recovery by about half so the group that
did not get the supplement the typical
recovery day was 22 days long the
supplement group it was cut down to 10
so this was a very very very impressive
result and so it seems to be a somewhat
High reward lowrisk option additionally
the other B vitamins like b6 and
b12 have
probably more limited research but
they're really plausible they're also
really safe they've been studied a lot
and a lot of unhealthy or risky
populations and they just don't really
have that many negative side effects so
sounds logical to try these ones um
there is a little bit of work here
particularly what I'm thinking of as
some rat studies in cases of things like
folate
deficiency when that happens a little
bit of a background there when you are
deficient in folate you have higher
levels of is called homosysteine and
homocysteine is highly associated with
additional oxidative stress and a whole
host of other negative Health Cascades
so really high homocysteine is is bad
news right um homosysteine is often also
elevated when B vitamins are too low in
general that alone is associated with
neuropathy of tbis brain atrophy
cognitive decline with aging and so on
and so forth and so the clinical trials
that have been done in this area where
they combine these B vitamins and
Omega-3s have been shown to reduce homoy
and that has then also been associated
with a reduction in cognitive decline so
if you can pay attention all those B
vitamins try to get them as high as as
reasonable or at least not in those
danger areas take a look at hosis and
pay attention to that and if you do that
that will give those Omega-3s a better
chance to work more effectively and you
should be in a better spot so what's
Rial flaven look like in terms of
supplementation and food one more time
the dosages that have been studied for
migraines and headaches and brain health
and things like that or 400 milligrams
per day one of the studies did that
dosage once per day another did it twice
per day but those are really really
common now you can look all over the
Internet and you will generally find
every multivitamin has R flaven but it's
not very much so multivitamins are not
going to be the place you can go to to
get enough B12 or B2 rather for this
issue you're going to have to go to
companies that make B2 specifically okay
in terms of timing again you want to
take this after your brain injury
certainly but the better option is just
to make sure your B stat status is high
enough prior to going in okay but if you
didn't do that or don't know you would
want to take this post injury time of
day doesn't matter at all some people
will feel a little bit of an energetic
effect so perhaps earlier in the morning
others don't but you might want to
consider that I'm not aware of any risks
associated with it obviously everything
has some risk of some dosage and some
people but for the most part there
there's very little harm here B vitamins
typically don't have many issues if you
overc consume them outside of perhaps
wasting your money I guess if you want
to think about it that way but there's
really very little consequences at
reasonable dosages so it should be okay
there if you want to get this from whole
food sources this is where things like
liver come in handy or fortified cereals
whey protein actually has a decent
amount uh beef liver specifically has
3.4 milligram of ribal flaven per 100 gr
whey protein is about half that I think
it's about two actually so it's not a
terrible source so you can run the math
very similar to how we just did it
before I won't drag you through it again
but if we have to eat something like 15
times is the amount of the serving size
I just listed to get to that 400
milligrams per day that's you know going
to be a pound a pound and a half sorry a
kilo or a kilo and a half of beef liver
per day so again theoretically possible
but just pretty unlikely or pretty
unrealistic for most people to get these
at this dosage through just food now
remember these are not daily amounts you
have to take we're talking about the
dosages specifically for a brain injury
and so it's actually not that crazy to
think you're taking it if you've
experienced something like this it's not
something that you need to do every day
your entire life next on our list is
Coline now this has a handful of
functions first it's helpful in
preserving that blood brain barrier
because it Wards off membrane breakdown
it's critical to that cell membrane so
it has a handful of effects there the
second big thing it does is it is the
primary precursor to the
neurotransmitter acetylcholine you may
remember that acetylcholine is the
primary neurotransmitter that's the
signal the molecular signal that goes
from one neuron to the next that
activates it we talked about this in a
little more detail in a previous episode
on muscle so you can go back to that to
learn more but the third thing it does
it is a precursor to that important
antioxidant glutathione so a handful of
functions here both structural damage
cellular communication and activation as
well as
antioxidant we also know from a lot of
research in the area of brain aging
dementia Alzheimer's and so forth that
higher dietary intake of choline is
strongly associated with decreases in
several biomarkers that are associated
with that Alzheimer's dementia and other
risk factors so from a dietary
perspective
from a molecular and mechanistic
perspective is starting to line up as a
pretty important molecule for both TBI
as well as long-term brain health to
summarize the collective evidence It is
Well tolerated and safe it's plausibly
helpful like I just described and
there's even some minor benefits in both
physiological and cognitive domains
following head trauma the most common
form of choline in the research is
what's called ceto choline or CD P
choline as you'll see it sometimes and
it's been tested in multiple TBI
randomized control trials in fact a
recent metaanalysis indicated that
there's about a 20% likelihood of
success or Effectiveness with
acetylcholine for TBI treatment so it's
not perfect but 20% is pretty good in my
opinion getting into the research just a
little bit further there's a handful of
animal and human studies that are worth
talking about at a very high level the
animal research looked at 100 Mig per
kilogram of body body weight per day and
I'm bringing up those numbers
intentionally I want to put some context
behind that honestly because I've just
heard people misinterpret this paper a
lot so 100 milligrams per kilogram per
day immediately after an injury which
resulted in significant improvements in
what's called spatial memory performance
now you can't simply
equate body weight here to humans you'll
get an absurd number that won't make
sense you it doesn't actually work that
way for details we don't want to talk
about now but this what this would
equate to is something like 60 to 70
milligrams per kilogram in
humans and that is high it's about 3 to
five times the dosages used in human
research but it's not impossible either
so I do want to acknowledge that those
numbers are again high but it's not
completely crazy either in fact some of
the studies at 250
milligrams helped with the blood brain
barrier breakdown and edema uh were
largely reduced in those trials and also
had benefits in hippocampal neuronal
death for the seven days following
injury so pretty good mechanisms from
the rat studies in terms of the human
you will see that the studies are mixed
okay one gram per day for 30 days has
been found to in at least mild TBI to
produce statistically significant
improvements in recognition memory which
is obviously an important Downstream
behavioral problem that's associated
with t eyes and that study was actually
repeated about 20 years after the
initial one and they used a pretty
similar protocol design and found
actually no difference in TPI symptoms I
think it was headaches sleepiness
dizziness and concentration and things
like that however what's really
important to note here is in this study
um the majority of the participants had
really minor tbis meaning their colc
Pathways were probably not affected this
is a classic case of something I warned
out the beginning or earlier in our
conversation if you're not actually
giving a supplement or taking a food
that the mechanism of effect is not the
mechanism of injury then you shouldn't
expect a benefit so I think this is
really a case of that I actually do feel
like the strength of the evidence for
coling is okay and reasonable but that
2023 follow-up study to me is not
indication that the original study was
flawed or didn't work but simply you had
mild injury that didn't result in damage
to that pathway so the benef the
supplement provided very limited or
mixed benefits in addition I know of two
meta analyses that reported generally
positive benefits here regardless of TBI
severity so that's some more information
of positive
benefit and the probably Landmark study
in this area came out fairly recently it
was called the cobrit study I think it
stands for like cocoline brain injury
treatment trial you know how scientists
always like to make these acronyms for
our big studies again honestly I feel
like this is being misinterpreted in my
opinion and so want to touch on this
just really briefly but in that they
found um no evidence of benefit for
cognitive function or cognitive status
90 days post injury with two grams a day
of cetola now a lot of people have used
that to say we told you it doesn't work
it doesn't work and that's fine you can
people can interpret how they will my
personal opinion on this study though is
that it's highly flawed
and I'm saying that because in it they
considered adherence to be 75% meaning
if the people in the study took their
cetto choline 75% of the time they were
considered to be adherent only
44% of their participants met that 75%
Mark
40% were considered to be non-adherent
so that means they took it less than 75%
and the rest they don't even know so for
me it's it's hard to suggest that it
didn't work work when the vast majority
of people didn't actually take it most
of the time and those that did was still
only 75% of the time so cool study
helped a lot add a lot of information in
my opinion to the database but I don't
think it should be interpreted as saying
that Coline then therefore doesn't work
or it's a myth or any of those other
more extreme interpretations of these
data more directly for the context of
our show today been done on football
players where brain coing
and specifically in the primary motor
cortex is known to diminish across the
season similar to what we saw earlier
with creatine probably as a result of
those continuous head impacts so
couldn't be inferred directly from this
study but you know pretty easy to make a
guess that's likely scenario and this
actually may contribute to that second
impact syndrome and accumulation of
damage so similar idea here as
creatine to me pretty strong case so
based on the different study designs
mixed results and other limitations the
soe for choline lands at a three so what
are we looking at in terms of food and
supplements well first of all you're not
going to find choline supplements on
their own very commonly it's almost
always going to be in the form of what's
called Alpha GPC or in the more direct
version of phospha choline now Alpha GPC
is immediately metabolized into
phospholine or PC once you orally ingest
it so you can think of these as similar
products many companies make either PC
straight or Alpha GPC or have a little
bit built into oftentimes like B
complexes dosages are usually a little
bit lower 20 to 30 milligrams if you're
getting the alpha GPC directly momentus
of course sponsor for the show as well
as other
companies generally will make dosages
300 to 400 milligram for serving so you
need to take you know three or so of
those to get to this dosage level but
you will find that fairly commonly okay
now in terms of timing you're probably
want to take something like 500
milligrams per day as a daily dosage
prophylactically however if you've had a
direct head injury this might be the
time to ramp up to 1 to two gr these
generally do have a neut Tropic effect
and so you would want to take these
earlier in the day so you certainly
don't have any problems cognitively or
with sleep later on in terms of food if
you need to get up to that 1 to two
grams after an acute injury you're
probably going to want to use
supplementation but it's quite easy to
get to that 500 that Baseline
prophylactic dosage straight out of food
a couple of eggs and some turkey will'll
almost always get you right there the
most common places to get chaned food
are meat poultry fish eggs dairy beans
cruciferous vegetables beef liver for
example has around 400 Mig per 100 G of
liver eggs it's about 150 milligrams per
egg and so you can actually see all
right three or four eggs in a day get
you really close to that 500 number most
people a couple of eggs little bit of
serving meat you're going to be right
there throughout the day which again
will put you in a pretty good spot the
average person though doesn't get enough
choline typical numbers in men is around
400 milligrams women is about 300 or
so which is well below the AI or
adequate intake which is you know 550
for men and 420 or so for women so you
would have to probably do something in
the neighborhood of like 12 eggs to get
you to that you know two grams colum per
day so like I said totally fine to get
this from food as your normal Baseline
Health strategy but if you did want to
get those upper dosage with an acute
injury you're probably going to have an
easier time getting a little bit of
supplementation rather than trying to
eat 14 or 15 eggs in a day all right
moving on to our next one we're looking
at Branch chain amino acids to clarify
when I say bcas I'm almost always
talking about three amino acids in
particular isoline Lucine and valine now
Lucine is the primary driver of muscle
growth or muscle protein synthesis which
is why there's so much steam behind
BCAAs for muscle growth we'll talk about
those details later but in general if
you get enough protein bcas are are not
really needed for muscle growth that
said does something different in the
brain the human data do suggest that the
severity of your TBI symptoms correlate
well with the degree of BCAA suppression
in the brain bigger drop in bcas more
symptoms the bcas have two big effects
one of them is the fact that they are
what's called a nitrogen donor and the
other is that they help Transportation
interference across the blood brain
barrier so let me walk you through what
those mean really quickly as it's
important to understand why they
actually work in this case but perhaps
are not so important for muscle growth
now when I say nitrogen donor what I
mean is they are specifically
used as in broken down to give off
nitrogen which can be used for glutamate
and Gaba I already talked about
glutamate earlier and how that is a
primary problem with extreme
excitotoxicity so getting too excited
turn turning too many neurons on now
both Gaba and glutamate are heavily
involved in TBI pathology like we just
talked about from the transporter
perspective when you eat protein the
amount or say it's food or supplement
the amount of bcas in your blood goes up
makes sense but a bunch of proteins in
your stomach they get broken down into
amino acids amino acids and your blood
go up if you ate a complete protein that
will come with a bunch of bcas the
amount of those go up in your blood now
as the BCA concentration goes up two
molecules called tryptophan and tyrosine
they happen to share the same
Transporters to get through the bloodb
brain barrier
so if you have this big rise in bcas in
your blood the bcas will block up those
Transporters which means the uptake of
tyrosine and tryptophan are blocked so
they're not going to get across the
blood rain barrier and not going to get
in the brain okay so the amount actually
in your brain of TNT tyrosine and
tryptophan go down what that does is
cause problems with things like
serotonin because TNT act as precursors
for serotonin which courses in a
precursor for melatonin and various
catamin right so this could be
contributing to the TBI induced sleep
problems and so you can see the basic
logic there the current evidence does
suggest that actually sleep is not
compromised with BCAAs but actually even
potentially improved I know of actually
a study coming to mind right now that
looked at 30 grams of BCAAs administered
twice per day found it actually improved
insomnia and other latency related
issues
uh this was study I think was in
veterans with chronic TBI and so we know
some about the mechanisms that I just
outlined has a potential to be
influencing some of our sleep related
problems and it seems to be causing a
positive and beneficial effect for Sleep
which is a huge concern and one of the
biggest symptoms associated with the
brain injury the S soe on BCAAs is
surprisingly a two remember one is best
five is worst on this scoring so the
data are actually pretty strong here it
is pretty clear that it works as much as
we can Define work there is extensive
evidence in posst Impact for both mild
and severe tbis the benefits range from
cognitive deficits so reductions in
cognitive deficits to what I just
described the some of these sleep wake
abnormalities with the main effects
probably being a correction of that
excitotoxicity issue um and some of the
Gaba and other glutamate problems that
that we just described probably the most
famous study in this area is called the
hit heads trial I believe this came out
in 2024 actually so pretty recent it was
a pilot randomized control trial they
had uh I think like 10 to 35 year olds
in there so teens pre-teens all the way
up to normal age and they followed them
for 3 weeks or 21 days post injury and
this was really cool they had I think
five arms in the study so some of the
participants just got a placebo and then
they broke up the rest of the
intervention by dosage so they got 15
grams a day 30 grams 45 or even 54 I'm
not sure why I 55 but they wanted to see
is there effect at all compared to
Placebo and if there is what's the
optimal dosage and they gave them five
different dosages from low dose to more
moderate to to pretty high and scaled
all the way up and one of the things
that they found was a pretty clear dose
response such that the most improvements
were found in that 54 gam per day
decreased symptoms of concussions a
faster and better return to Baseline
there weren't not benefits actually in
what was called processing speed so that
have been shown in some of the earlier
studies we talked about but they didn't
find that here for whatever reason but
they had all those other benefits one
more time highlights the fact that not
every supplement not every food not
every nutrient fixes every problem okay
so benefits here in the concussion
symptoms but not necessarily the
processing speed but the effects one
more time were dose dependent and one
more time like we keep bringing up there
was no adverse effects reported the data
that we currently have suggests up to 55
or 54 G per day more specifically is a
dosage you would want to make sure
you're at that higher dosage past injury
you can be a much smaller one just
honestly make sure your protein intake
is high enough you can use whatever
number you like we've talked many times
though I personally like one gram of
protein per pound of body weight if
you're at that you're probably getting
enough BCAAs at Baseline and then we
would go to only this higher dose
postbrain injury to break this down
foodwise BCAAs it's protein it's dairy
product it's meat and poultry most
meat's going to be 3 to four gram of
bcas per 100 gram of serving and so
similar math the way we've done before
okay this is going to result in you
having to have like 40 or 50 ounces of
meat per
day not something you need Baseline but
in these small cases again I'm don't
want you to feel like I'm pushing you to
supplements but it is just significantly
easier here for small times and for
specific scenarios of a brain injury to
go to supplementation here our next
micronutrient is
magnesium oh my goodness could I go on
and on and on about the physiological
benefits of magnesium it is involved in
well over 600 reactions in your body
from cell signaling vascular function
ATP production protein synthesis uh
neuroplasticity learning memory and I
could basically think of anything that
happens in your body and magnesium's
Central to that I don't have to draw
this out then it's pretty easy for you
to assume this is going to be a
important role in your brain pre and
post injury we also have very strong
data if you are deficient in magnesium
you have associations with a host of
comorbidities health conditions type two
diabetes metabolic syndrome hypertension
headaches is another common one
migraines heart disease so on and so
forth we know that it probably inhibits
receptors that are directly targets of
anti-depressants as well and is a strong
contributor to that brain excitotoxicity
after injury so you do not want to be
deficient in magnesium you can listen to
read almost anything in the sports
performance realm and you will see
magnesium as a top tier supplementation
it is really robust and a a strong line
of evidence and and recommended by again
many people in this field but
surprisingly the S soe is only three
here there's a well documented drop in
magnesium especially near Central
neurons after a TBI and the extent of
that drop is associated with the
severity of the injury and the level of
Behavioral disturbances so not only the
injury but your symptoms as well animal
and human research here from the animals
It's associated with edema brain and
blood concentrations calcium problems
like we talked about earlier um these
are going to result in those behavioral
modifications memory cognitive function
spatial and working memory and so on and
so forth from the actual human stuff
couple of studies that are worth drawing
attention to here one looked at acute
tbis in kids and so a significant
reduction in post concussion severity
scores 48 hours after the injury when
they used 400 mg of magnesium twice per
day now another study was used a similar
design and didn't find a benefit but
this was actually using magnesium from
an IV for 5 days now no one really
actually knows why this one trial worked
the other one didn't the obvious thought
is maybe there's something that happens
when you adjust it through your stomach
that aids in digestion or makes it more
bioavailable but when you took it with
the IV it didn't to me that's honestly
not a great answer but I don't have any
other reason to think that that happened
so really honestly to summarize here it
is very very safe it's very little harm
it has so many other health and
performance related benefits there's so
many Health consequences
that are associated with magnesium
deficiency it helps with symptoms and
behaviors that are Hallmarks of TBI like
we've talked
about so I know the soe is technically
three but personally it's it's about as
high in the list as I could think one
supplement could be the dosages we
described one more time 400 milligrams
per day the timing doesn't matter you'll
want to have some in their pre as well
as post injury and you could take it at
any point in the day now depending on
the type or form that you use you might
want to take it later in the evening
some people report and depending on the
type magnesium helps you fall asleep I
personally feel no effect at all but
most people do I still then take my
magnesium at night just because just in
case there is all kinds of forms you've
heard of magnesium threate at this point
bisglycinate malate and right now I
don't know of any compelling evidence to
suggest one of those forms is any better
than another obviously magnesium 38 has
become more popular recently and that
may turn out to be more effective it may
not I'm not sure there's just not enough
data for us to have a really an answer
at this point and so you can take
whatever form sits best with you the
obvious risks associated with magnesium
are the GI distress bisglycinate malate
3 and8 are generally pretty well handled
and so you you shouldn't have too many
issues with it if you want to get it
strictly from food you're looking now at
things like pumpkin seeds chia seeds
almonds and spinach
uh typically I think pumpkin seeds are
about the highest you'll find they've
got around 200 milligrams of magnesium
per 100 grams
roasted again you can do some math there
and realize all right that's at least
200 grams of roasted pumpkin seeds I'd
have to get to get to my you know 400
milligrams which is honestly quite a lot
not impossible some people eat tons of
almonds and spinach and things like that
especially vegetarians and vegans but it
is quite a bit given how cheap effective
and easy to handle and how many other
things are benefited with magnesium as a
supplement n we use it pretty commonly
our final food item to discuss is what's
called anthocyans now these come almost
always from blueberries so henceforward
I'll call these blueberry anthos that's
how I refer to it now these are phyto
chemicals in the flavonoid family
there's over 700 known antho molecules
and we're honestly basically just
learning about this stuff so we have a
ton of improvements needed a ton more
analysis and understanding of mechanisms
and so on and so forth but there's
enough here to go on at this point we
know that anthos are involved in
cardiovascular disease metabolic
syndrome type 2 diabetes cancers Visions
skin Health inflammation
neurodegenerative disorders and probably
50 more things really ubiquitous really
robust and critical to a bunch of human
functions TBI
specifically animal research here
blueberry supplements or blueberry
extracts post injury have been shown to
improve what's called brain derived
neurotropic factor or what you may have
heard of as
bdnf which is inversely correlated with
indirect markers of memory performance
and cognition now a similar study has
found that blueberries also protect
against oxidative stress which makes a
ton of sense you've all probably heard
about the antioxidant properties
Associated blueberries and blueberry
extracts so this is no surprise for most
people the soe for anthos is a three and
in terms of human data I don't think
there's a single RCT randomized control
trial that exists for blueberries and
TBI at this point that said there have
been studies and many rcts um some
effect fact that are range from
developmental to aging to clinical
populations on brain health and so this
is a classic example of where we can
infer some things from General brain
health over to TBI at a pretty low risk
High reward possibility the collective
evidence um indicates that it does help
with attention memory executive function
there's a lot of evidence specifically
we use a handful of papers that have
been done looking at blueberries prior
to golf and enhancing brain performance
in sport context so there's a lot out
there we know it works but we also know
we're missing a lot of the details
because of what I just described earlier
it's pretty new couple of examples one
study in kids in particular looked at 15
or 30 grams of freeze dried wild
blueberries and saw significant
improvements in cognitive function in a
dose dependent fashion more blueberries
the better uh other work has been done
in in older adults looking at things
like 100 milligrams blueberry extracts
and seeing a better episodic memory
performance reduced cardiovascular
disease uh and so on and so forth so um
what this would look like from a whole
food source you know to get something
like 500 millgram of the anthos you need
100 gr of
blueberries which is I think a cup has
150 so I'll translate that for you a
little bit you have a couple blueberries
and you're probably hitting your numbers
it's really that easy I would actually
say that of all the things we've
discussed so far today this is the
easiest one to get out of straight food
you will be hardpressed to find a
program that ever comes out of myself
our rapid health and performance company
or any other one that I'm associated
with that doesn't have a cup of
blueberri in it and it's for these
reasons that manymore so it's a pretty
easy number to hit pretty consistent and
has a lot of benefits right I will also
tell you people love to give blueberry
all the credit here but it's not the
only food item that's got the anthos in
it strawberries cranberries they have it
too there's not as much data I don't
actually know if there's any data but I
imagine if they did those studies you'd
probably find the same benefit so I'm
actually not as particular on this one I
don't have evidence to support myself
but I don't think it's that big of a
stretch to think the same chemicals in
this case that are in blueberries
probably also exist in raspberries and
strawberries and other similar forms so
um we will spread our berries out but if
you want to stick to giving all the love
to blueberries you're not going to hurt
my feelings as far as I understand it
that represents all the evidence on food
related items one can take for brain
health tbis and concussions the only
thing I'm aware of that's actually
detrimental for brain healing is
caffeine
and there's enough evidence here that
this is probably pretty bad news when
trying to heal from a brain injury it
causes neurovascular constriction it
leads to less blood flow we know that
caffeine consumers are more susceptible
uh to to diminished emotional health bad
Sleep Quality depression and somatic
symptoms with brain injuries and so what
my recommendation here would be overc
consumption is the problem do not over
consume caffeine if you've experienced a
brain injury I don't think there's any
reason to think caffeine consumption is
giving give you more risk to have a
brain injury but if you have one you you
want to make sure you're really careful
ask your doctor check in there but
that's the only one on our list that we
have reason to think that you should
avoid that concludes today's episode on
nutrition for brain injury TBI and
concussion I think it's worth reminding
you though that if it's good for
preventing and returning faster from a
brain injury it's probably safe to
assume it's also good for prank
performance as well as long-term Health
my goal of today as always was to
provide you with a ton of information so
that you can be excited you can learn
you have some things to try but to also
be fair with the state of the data and
you can make your decision about what
you want to do or not do based upon that
given this was episode 10 not only are
we done with today's discussion but we
are done with season one a perform with
Dr Andy Galpin I can't thank you all for
the support I seriously was
overwhelmed with comments from people I
know don't know it it was blew past my
expectations and so I really just cannot
thank you all enough if you're a new
listener this is maybe your first
episode you can go back and check out
all previous Nine episodes on perform
podcast.com you can check out the notes
you can go to YouTube and you can see
the exact sections of a particular video
if you're interested in that and we've
made it as easy as possible hopefully
for you to go straight to the
information you're looking for
and not spend time on things you are not
I can also share with you another fun
announcement and that is that season two
is officially been confirmed it's going
to be coming out pretty soon if you want
to know more about when that does hit
the radio waves you can stay tuned of
course on my social media but also I
would recommend signing up for our
newsletter finishing us up here I I
cannot conclude this in season without
some very specific thank yous first of
all to all the sponsors it was
overwhelming your support the people
jumped on board quickly and we're really
really helpful so this show would not
have existed without them so I know ad
reads are a thing but please do me a
solid if you enjoyed any part of any of
the episodes of the Season go check out
the sponsors they really are phenomenal
products I got to thank my special man
Vin dog you know who you are helped me a
ton in preparing for this he's not the
front of the camera kind of guy so
appreciate it Vince Natasha of course my
wife super super supportive and all the
time it spent to come up here and get
this stuff done my students former and
past and current uh could not have done
any of the stuff that allowed me to be
up here without all of your support and
truly doing all the work in the lab same
thing for all of my colleagues and
fellow scientists whom helped me
directly with this show or indirectly
and that I stole your research or read
it at least and was able to have
information to share with people so
science is not easy and a lot of times
people don't get the credit for it and
and I thank you all for your
contribution all of my teammates and
colleagues at my company's rapid health
and performance biomolecular athlete
absolute rest and vitality again tons
and tons of support for everyone so I
appreciate that and then finally of
course my man here and my boys here at
scom and of course Dr Andrew huberman
love you all super appreciative of it
thank you all so much for joining on
this ride and I'll see you next season
thank you for joining for today's
episode our goal is to share exciting
scientific Insight that helps you
perform at your absolute best if the
show resonates with you and and you want
to help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the
world there are a few ways that you can
support first you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube Spotify and apple and on
Apple and Spotify you can leave up to a
five-star review given that we're a new
podcast subscribing and leaving a review
really does help us a lot second please
check out our sponsors the show would
not exist without them and they really
are exceptional products and services
and then finally you can share today's
episode with a friend who you think
would enjoy it
if you have any content questions or
suggestions please put those in the
comment section on YouTube I really do
try to read these and see what you have
to say if you have yet to sign up for
our monthly newsletter you can do so at
perform podcast.com our newsletter
provides episode summaries with the key
takeaways for each and every episode of
the podcast this includes topics like
how to improve your VO2 max how to build
muscle mass and muscle strength how to
optimize your sleep for high performance
and much more to sign up just go to
perform podcast.com click newsletter at
the top of the screen and then enter
your email address once you sign up you
receive access to all of our newsletters
I use my Instagram and Twitter also
exclusively for scientific communication
so those are great places to follow
along for more learning my handle is Dr
Andy Galpin on both platforms thank you
for listening and never forget in the
famous words of Bill Bowerman if you
have a body you're an athlete